A Finding Aid to the Rackstraw Downes Research Material Concerning Fairfield Porter, 1962-2000, bulk 1970-1979, in the Archives of American Art AAA.downrack
Archives of American Art
Rackstraw Downes research material concerning Fairfield Porter
bulk 1970-1979
1962-2000
AAA.downrack
Archives of American Art
1 Linear feet
TThe Rackstraw Downes research material concerning Fairfield Porter measure 1.0 linear foot and date from 1962 to 2000, with the bulk of the material dating from 1970-1979. Downes used the material to compile, edit and write the introduction to Fairfield Porter: Art In Its Own Terms - Selected Criticism 1935-1975 published in 1979. Research materials include articles about Porter, exhibition catalogs, photocopies of letters and some original correspondence, theses and manuscripts. Also included are project files for the publication of Art In Its Own Terms.
Downes, Rackstraw
Biographical/Historical note
Rackstraw Downes (1939-), a landscape painter and author in New York City, edited and wrote the introduction to Fairfield Porter: Art In It's Own Terms: Selected Criticism 1935-1975. Born in Kent, England, Downes received a B.A. in English literature from Cambridge University in 1961 and earned an M.F.A. from the Yale School of Arts in 1961. Downes was personally acquainted with Porter.
Fairfield Porter (1907-1975), a painter, art critic and poet, resided in Southampton, New York. Porter was a strong advocate for figure painting. He wrote for ArtNews and The Nation, and eventually became art editor for The Nation.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by Rackstraw Downes in 2012.
Scope and Contents note
The Rackstraw Downes research material concerning Fairfield Porter measure 1.0 linear foot and date from 1962 to 2000, with the bulk of the material dating from 1970-1979. Downes used the material to compile, edit and write the introduction to Fairfield Porter: Art In Its Own Terms - Selected Criticism 1935-1975 published in 1979. Research materials include articles about Porter, exhibition catalogs, photocopies of letters and some original correspondence, theses and manuscripts. Also included are project files for the publication of Art In Its Own Terms.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series 1: Research Material, 1962-2000 (0.7 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Files on Fairfield Porter: Art In Its Own Terms, Selected Criticism 1935-1975, 1973-1992 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Porter, Fairfield; Art critics -- New York (State) -- Southampton; Photographs
- Research Material, 1962-2000; Series 1; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains many photocopies of Porter's writings published as early as 1935. Photocopies of letters from Fairfield Porter are to various recipients including: John MacWhinnie, Robert Dash, David Shapiro, Ron Padgett, Edith Schloss, Frank O'Hara, and Howard Griffin. Downes's correspondence with Fairfield and Anne Porter are the original letters, as are those from Porter to Poppy and Lucien Day.
  After the publication was completed, Downes continued to add material. He subsequently compiled the bibliography included in the exhibition catalog, Fairfield Porter: Realist Painter in an Age of Abstraction, published in 1982 by the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, MA.
  - Printed Material - Essays by Fairfield Porter (1958-1961), circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Printed Material - Articles about Fairfield Porter, 1970-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Printed Material - Essays and Reviews of Art by Fairfield Porter (1935-1974), circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Printed Material - Exhibition Catalogs, 1969-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material - Reviews and Articles, 1969-1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Theses and Manuscripts by Anne Devaney, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Theses and Manuscripts by Ted Leigh, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Theses and Manuscripts by John T. Spike, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Chronology and Partial Bibliography, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bibliography for Boston Museum of Fine Arts, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Excerpts from Fairfield Porter letters (1968-1975), circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters from Fairfield Porter to Howard Griffin (1977), circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters from Fairfield Porter (1961-1975), circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters from Fairfield Porter to Frank O'Hara (1955), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters from Anne Porter to Rackstraw Downes, 1976-1997 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letters from Fairfield Porter to Rackstraw Downes, 1966-1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters from Fairfield Porter to Poppy and Lucien Day, 1962-1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters from Rackstraw Downes to Fairfield Porter, 1966-1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Research Notebook, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Files on Fairfield Porter: Art In Its Own Terms, Selected Criticism 1935-1975, 1973-1992; Series 2; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  This series contains material related to the book's publication and includes permissions, correspondence, some financial records, and the manuscript.
  - Introduction and Outline, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Photographs for Publication, circa 1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Permissions- Original, 1978-1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous Fairfield Porter Writings (circa 1940-1973), circa 1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Financial Reports, Expenses and Reviews, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence with Taplinger Publishing, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Manuscript, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 30-33)